Last time we left off by creating a bar chart of Pokemon by their first type.
上个视频中 我们为宝可梦的第一属性绘制了柱状图
I've performed some data wrangling to obtain a data frame
这里我对数据进行了整理 创建了一个 新的 DataFrame
with both first and second types in a single column.
把两种属性都放入了同一列数据中
I've also created some variables to get the types in order of frequency,
我还创建了一些变量 按频率大小排列了属性
and then plotted those counts in a bar chart.
并将数量统计结果绘制成条形图
One thing that I'm interested in now,
现在我想知道
is what proportion of Pokemon have each type.
各属性的宝可梦占比
While I might be able to estimate this from
虽然知道宝可梦总数后
the plot by knowing the total number of Pokemon,
可以根据这张图进行估算
it's probably better just to show it directly in the visualization.
但如果直接把占比可视化出来 可能会直观很多
One way of doing this is to use Matplotlib to change
为此 我们可以
the tick marks from leveling absolute counts, to relative counts.
用 Matplotlib 将轴刻度从绝对计数改为相对计数
Let's start by creating a list of tick positions.
首先 让我们创建刻度位置列表
We start by computing the length of the longest bar in terms of proportion.
为此 我们要先把最长条形的长度转为百分比
The original Pokemon data frame gives us the denominator,
因此 我们用原始 DataFrame pokemon 求出分母
and we use value counts to get the numerator.
然后用数量统计值作分子
Now, we use NumPy's a range function,
现在 用 NumPy 函数 arange
to produce a set of evenly spaced proportioned values
生成一个等差比值列表
between zero and the max in steps of 2%,
在 0 和最大值之间 步长为 2%
and store the values in the tick props variable.
将这个数值赋给变量 tick_props
I'm also using a list comprehension to create
我还用了列表推导式
an additional variable tick names to apply to the tick labels.
创建了另一个变量 tick_names 做为刻度标签
These strings will show the proportions with a consistent two decimal places.
这些字符串会以两位小数的形式表示百分比
Now we're ready to modify our plot.
现在我们可以修改图表了
To change the tick locations and labels,
要修改刻度标签的位置
we use Matplotlib's X tick's function.
就用 Matplotlib 的函数 xticks
The first argument sets the tick positions.
要设置的第一个参数是刻度位置
Since the counts are still an absolute value,
由于现在数量统计仍是绝对值
we need to multiply tick props by the number of Pokemon to get their position correct.
所以要让刻度百分比 tick_props 乘以 n_pokemon 从而获取正确的刻度位置
The second argument sets the tick labels.
第二个参数是刻度标签
We need to use both arguments here,
这里两个参数都要输入
since the positions and their values, are different.
因为刻度位置和值是不同的
Finally, we use the X label function to change the x-axis label from the default count,
最后 用函数 xlabel 把 x 轴标签从默认的 count
to a more appropriate proportion.
改为更恰当的 proportion
The resulting plot shows us that about 16% of all Pokemon include
从修改后的条形图可知 水属性约占 16%
the water type all the way down to only 4% that include the ice type.
冰属性占 4% 等等
Alternatively, maybe we want to have the axes in terms of counts,
我们也可以让横轴表示数量统计
and use text on the bars to show proportion.
然后在条形上用文本标出百分比
This is where the flexibility of Matplotlib can shine.
此时 Matplotlib 的灵活性就凸显出来了
We use a loop to place text elements one by one.
我们可以用一个循环逐个放置文本元素
The first argument to the text function is the X position,
函数 text 的第一个参数是 x 的位置
just after the end of the bar.
就在条形末端
The second argument is the Y position,
第二个参数是 y 的位置
which starts at zero and increments with the loop.
从 0 开始 随着循环逐渐增量
The third argument is the string to be printed, the percentage.
第三个参数是要输出的字符串 即百分比
Finally, I'm going to add an optional parameter VA
最后 我还要加一个可选参数 va
to center the vertical alignment of text on each bar.
使每个条形的文本垂直居中对齐
The final plot looks like this.
最终效果如图